Guide to the David Abrahamsen Research Files,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
David Abrahamsen Research Files,
1906-1990
Abrahamsen, David, 1903-2002.
1.26 linear ft. (3 document boxes).
Columbia University Rare Book and Manuscript Library, New York, NY 10027.
MS#0004
4078348
The David Abrahamsen Research Files consist primarily of drafts and notes for Abrahamsen's studies on Jack the Ripper and Richard Nixon. Correspondence with David Berkowitz, the Son of Sam serial killer, is also held in the collection.
Historical Note
David Abrahamsen was a forensic psychiatrist, author, and psychoanalyst who was known for his books analyzing the personalities of major criminals, such as Jack the Ripper and David Berkowitz (Son of Sam). Abrahamsen was born on June 23, 1903 in Trondheim, Norway. He received his medical degree in 1929 from the Royal Frederick University in Oslo. After working at several clinics in Europe, Abrahamsen immigrated to the United States. In 1942, he began working as a lecturer and research associate at the College of Physicians and Surgeons, Columbia University. He also maintained a private practice. From 1949 to 1953, Abrahamsen was Chair of the Columbia University Forum for the Study and Prevention of Crime. Throughout his long career, Abrahamsen was affiliated with a number of institutions such as the New School for Social Research, Yale Law School, the Foundation for the Prevention of Addictive Disease, and multiple hospitals. He was also a prolific writer, penning over ten books and many articles on criminal behavior. David Abrahamsen died in May 2002 at the age of 98.
Abrahamsen is perhaps best known for this involvement in the Son of Sam trial. In 1977, David Berkowitz was arrested for committing a series of six murders in New York City. David Abrahamsen was called in to assist the Brooklyn district attorney in determining whether or not Berkowitz was mentally fit to stand trial. Abrahamsen concluded that Berkowitz was competent and the trial moved onward. Berkowitz was sentenced to 365 years in prison and corresponded with Abrahamsen through two of those years. This correspondence allowed Abrahamsen to publish several scientific papers analyzing Berkowitz's personality. Abrahamsen also researched and psychoanalyzed Jack the Ripper which resulted in the book Murder and Madness: The Secret Life of Jack the Ripper (1992). Using police reports and medical records, Abrahamsen attempted to deconstruct the motivation behind the killings as well as to point toward potential suspects.
Nixon vs. Nixon is an analysis of former president, Richard Nixon. Relying primarily on interviews with individuals who knew Nixon at various points in his life, Abrahamsen presented a portrait of a very troubled individual. Although unable to actually interview Nixon in person, Abrahamsen used secondary research to supplement his analysis.
Scope and Content
The David Abrahamsen Research Files document analyzes conducted by Abraham on the criminal mind, in particular Jack the Ripper, Richard Nixon, and the Son of Sam killer, David Berkowitz. The bulk of the records are research notes, drafts, and articles written by Abrahamsen. There is a small amount of correspondence.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in three series:
Series I: Correspondence, 1938-1981
Series II: Subject Files, 1906-1978
Series III: Research Projects, 1944-1990
Subseries III.1: David Berkowitz, 1979,
Subseries III.2: Jack the Ripper, 1944-1990
Subseries III.3: Nixon vs. Nixon, 1960-1977
Subjects
Abrahamsen, David, 1903-2002.; Berkowitz, David Richard, 1953-; Nixon, Richard M. (Richard Milhous), 1913-1994.; Criminal psychology.; Murder--Case studies.; Psychiatrists; Drafts.; Personal correspondence.; Photographs.
Access Restrictions
This collection has no restrictions.
This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
Gift of Dr. David Abrahamsen, 1982.
- Series I: Correspondence, 1938-1981
  Most of the letters in Series I are from David Berkowitz, the Son of Sam serial killer. Written while incarcerated in Attica, Berkowitz corresponded regularly with Abrahamsen over a two year period. Much of the subject matter consists of Berkowitz trying to self-analyze about why he committed crimes. Abrahamsen continuously asked questions about Berkowitz's family, his upbringing, and his relationships with other people. There are a few letters from Jessamyn West, a distant relative of Nixon who assisted Abrahamsen while he was working on his book Nixon vs. Nixon.
  - Berkowitz, David
    - 1979 February-July (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 1979 August-1980 February (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - 1980 March-1981 January (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - 1981 February-August (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - B, 1945-1947 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - E through G, 1938-1949, 1957-1958, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - L, 1945-1965 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - M through O, 1945-1952 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - S through T, 1945-1952, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - West, Jessamyn, 1974-1976 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Series II: Subject Files, 1906-1978
  This small series contains documents with related correspondence concerning Adlai Stevenson's presidential run, articles written by psychologist Otto Weininger, and printed material from a conference sponsored by Columbia University for the study and prevention of crime. Abrahamsen presented at the conference and there are copies of his talk.
  - Columbia University Forum for the Study and Prevention of Crime, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Stevenson, Adlai, 1952-1953 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Weininger, Otto, 1906, 1929-1947, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Series III: Research Projects, 1944-1990
  Series III is the largest series of the collection and is comprised of files regarding three research projects: Nixon vs. Nixon: An Emotional Tragedy, Confessions of Son of Sam, and Murder and Madness: The Secret Life of Jack the Ripper.
  - Subseries III.1: David Berkowitz, 1979
    Interviews of David Berkowitz along with writings by him are held in this subseries.
    - Childhood, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Starkweather Excerpts with Notes, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Interview, 1979 May 17 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Notarized Affidavits, 1979 May 17 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Subseries III.2: Jack the Ripper, 1944-1990
    The majority of the records in this subseries are drafts of Abrahamsen's manuscript. These drafts are heavily edited and illustrate the process Abrahamsen went through in order to create the final product. Correspondence with research institutions and medical doctors in England, research notes, and articles regarding personality and crime (many written by Abrahamsen) are also in this subseries.
    - Articles, 1944-1952, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Correspondence, 1988-1989 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Drafts
      - Chapters 1 through 3, undated, 1984, (2 Folders) (Box 1, Folder 20 to 21)
      - Chapter 3, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
      - Chapter 4, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
      - Chapter 5, undated, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 24)
      - Chapter 6, undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
      - Chapters 6 through 8, undated, (2 Folders) (Box 1, Folder 26 to 27)
      - Chapter 7, undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
      - Chapter 8, undated, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 29)
      - Footnotes, undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Research Files, undated, 1981-1990, (2 Folders) (Box 1, Folder 31 to 32)
  - Subseries III.3: Nixon vs. Nixon, 1960-1977 (Box 2)
    Subseries III.3 is composed of research files with accompanying notes, correspondence with individuals who had some connection with Richard Nixon, early photographs of Nixon's family, and a draft of the manuscript with edits. Of interest are a series of interviews conducted by Abrahamsen with people who knew Nixon as a child and an adult, including a White House correspondent and Nixon's longtime campaign manager.
    - Correspondence, 1975-1976 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Draft, 1977, (3 Folders) (Box 2, Folder 2 to 4)
    - Nixon Film, undated (Box 3)
    - Interviews, 1975-1976 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Photographs, undated, 1960s-1970s (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Research Files, 1970s (Box 2, Folder 7)